The following content is
provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help
MIT OpenCourseWare
continue to offer high-quality
educational resources for free.
To make a donation or to
view additional materials
from hundreds of MIT courses,
visit MIT OpenCourseWare
at ocw.mit.edu.
GILBERT STRANG: So just
to orient where we are,
today starts a new chapter
about low-rank matrices.
So that's an important
bunch of matrices.
They can be truly low-rank,
like uv transpose.
That's a rank 1.
And we have some
questions about those.
And then later in
the chapter, we'll
meet matrices that are
approximately low-rank, where
the singular values
drop off like crazy.
And those are quite
remarkable matrices.
So this is my topic
at the beginning--
and if it doesn't
take the whole hour,
I want to go back to
a topic in chapter 2--
that should be 2.4--
where we were last time.
Good.
So that's for later in the hour.
This is for now.
Let's focus on this.
So what's the question there?
I start with the
identity matrix.
I perturb it by a
matrix of rank 1.
And I ask what the inverse is.
So I'm making a small
change in the matrix.
When I say small
change, I don't mean
that the numbers are small.
In fact, uv transpose could
be the all 1's matrix,
or the all millions
matrix, even.
But its rank is small.
That's the idea of small
that's important here.
And I would like to know
what the inverse is.
So that's the
question here in 4.1.
And there's a famous formula
that has at least three names,
and probably more, and it's
also called the matrix inversion
formula in signal processing.
And let me write
down the example.
So I start with the
identity matrix.
I do a rank 1 perturbation.
And I want to know,
what's the inverse?
And I'll write down the answer
and check that it's correct.
So I'm perturbing
the identity matrix
in this case, whose inverse
is also the identity matrix.
So I'm going to write the
answer as a perturbation of I.
And the question is, what
is that perturbation?
And it's a famous formula.
There is a uv transpose
that comes in,
copied from there, divided
by 1 minus v transpose u.
Now, let's first of
all just see that this
is a reasonable formula.
So u a column-- u and v are
column vectors, as always.
So uv transpose is a
matrix, column times row.
And it's being subtracted
from the identity.
And over here on this side,
I have uv transpose-- again,
a rank 1 matrix--
divided by a number.
So that's the point.
This is a number--
a 1 by 1 matrix, you could say.
So the point of this formula
is to find the inverse of an n
by n matrix in terms
of the inverse of a 1
by 1 matrix, which is a lot
simpler and easier to do.
I mean, that right-hand
side is clearly easy.
And let's see what other
things it tells us.
So this was a rank 1
perturbation in the identity.
Then when I invert, I get--
look at this.
This is also a rank 1.
That's a number.
In fact, it's the
very same rank 1
that we had there
in this nice case.
So conclusion-- if I
change a matrix by rank 1,
I change its inverse by rank 1.
That doesn't seem
completely obvious
until you go to figure it out.
When you figure it out, you
get a formula that tells you.
Well, so far what I'm perturbing
is the identity matrix.
When I get here, I'm going
to perturb any matrix.
And I'm going to reach
the same conclusion.
If this is rank 1, then
the change in the inverse
is also rank 1.
But let's see it first for
a equal to the identity.
So I guess I have two
or three questions.
One would be, how do you
check that this is correct?
Again, remember what it's doing.
It's pretty neat.
It's computing an n by n inverse
in terms of a 1 by 1 inverse.
It's a number.
And that's certainly
a favorable exchange.
So it's a formula that
you want and a formula
that's quite useful.
Let me just check
the formula before I
talk about how it's useful.
So how shall I check it?
I guess, if this is
claimed to be the inverse,
then let's just che--
so this will be the check.
I'll multiply by that, I
plus uv transpose over 1
minus v transpose u,
the claimed inverse.
And what am I hoping to get
from this multiplication?
AUDIENCE: I.
GILBERT STRANG: I. I'm
hoping that, that result is
the identity matrix.
So I'm just going to
do it out, and we'll
see the identity appear.
So that times I-- so let me
just write that part first,
I minus uv transpose.
And now I minus uv
transpose times this--
so that's I minus
uv transpose times
uv transpose over 1
minus v transpose u.
It's just multiplying
it out and seeing
that we get the identity.
I see the identity there.
So I guess, I hope that
all this part reduces to--
what does it reduce to?
Let me do that numerator there.
So that's uv transpose minus u--
ooh-- minus u times
v transpose u--
do you see what's
happening here--
v transpose.
The key is that when I
multiplied that times
that, I've got four
things in a row.
And I do the middle pair first.
Because that's a
number, v transpose u.
So I had uv transpose from
that and uv transpose times
that number minus--
do you see-- what
have I got here?
I've got--
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
GILBERT STRANG: Yeah.
I've got uv transpose.
Now I factor out a 1
minus v transpose u,
which is just what I want.
I factor the 1 minus v
transpose u out of here.
It's there.
Cancel those.
And then I'm left with a
uv transpose, which cancels
that and leaves the identity.
It's kind of magic.
Of course, somebody had
to figure out that formula
in the first place.
I could do the next one, if
you like, since I'm on a roll.
Suppose I take this second one,
now what's the difference in--
it's uv transpose, but those
are larger letters, the u
and the v. So what am
I meaning by those?
Those are matrices.
This is a bigger rank.
u has k columns.
v transpose has k rows.
That product uv
transpose is k by k.
So let me see what I think
the formula would be.
So now, I minus uv
transpose inverse--
so this is n by k times k by n.
So it's n by n matrix.
And this is the ide--
identity of this.
But its rank is--
what is the rank of that now?
AUDIENCE: k.
GILBERT STRANG: k.
Right.
So I have here, the whole
thing is the inverse
of an n by n matrix.
So I have an n by n matrix.
Let me put that up here,
n by n matrix to invert.
There it is.
I'm going to write
down the formula.
And you're going to be
able to write it down,
because it's just
copied from that one.
And you'll see that it
involves a k by k inverse.
So I have an n by
n matrix to invert,
but I don't have to do that.
I can switch it to
a k by k matrix.
That's pretty nice.
So let's do it.
So I'm basically gonna
copy that I plus u--
now, I've matrices.
So that's an inverse,
but I can't leave it
as a denominator.
Because through here, we're
talking about a k by k matrix.
So I have to put it like any
matrix inverse, Ik minus v
transpose u inverse.
So I'm just copying
this formula,
wisely taking the u
first, then this part,
then finally, the v transpose.
I put this one up.
This one now has made
that one obsolete.
This was the case k
equal to 1 over here.
But I think it helps to see it.
It certainly helps me
to see the formula first
for a rank 1 perturbation, which
is a very likely possibility,
and then see that we have a
totally analogous formula.
It's sort of fun to check it.
So I plan to do the same check.
But I'll just notice here
that I have a k by k inverse.
So I'm exchanging something
that's a perturbation of n
by n identity, an n
by n matrix, to have
to invert something
that's a k by k matrix,
perturbing the k by k
identity, much smaller.
In that case, k was 1.
So are you good for
checking it now?
So I want to
multiply that by this
and hopefully get
In, the identity.
This is the n by n identity.
I haven't given credit to
the two or three or four,
or possibly 11 people,
who found this formula.
And I'm not see-- oh,
yeah, here are their names.
Is it OK to make them famous
by putting their names up here?
Yes.
Sherman-- and I couldn't
tell you who did what.
Morrison, Woodbury, and
then no doubt others--
maybe one of them
did this rank 1 case,
and then another generalized it.
And then you could see from the
outline there that eventually
we'll-- we can perturb
a matrix A. Of course,
that's not going to be much
harder than the identity.
Let's do just one
more check, and then
show how it could be used.
I multiply that by that.
Can we do that--
this thing times this, and
hope to get the identity?
So first, I'll write
down this thing.
So I won't put equal, because
I'm multiplying that by that.
So I get In minus uv transpose.
On the left side, of course,
I'm getting the identity,
and hoping I'm getting
the identity on the right.
So I'm multiplying by this.
I did it there.
Now I have to put I
minus uv transposed.
It takes faith here. u I
minus v transpose u inverse v
transpose--
gulp.
Shall I just leave it there?
Or you're-- had
lunch, you're strong.
Let's see what we can do.
This part-- fine.
This part-- oh, boy.
What do I do here?
That trick is going to be that
this dopey-looking thing there
can be written differently.
Well, just tell
me what it equals.
It equals u minus
uv transpose u.
Everybody sees that.
But now what am I going to do?
I'm going to put the
parentheses differently.
I'm bringing u, the u that
was on the right up there--
I'm going to put it on the left.
You see that?
So this is obviously u
minus uv transpose u.
And now I'm going to
write it another time.
It's u times I
minus v transpose u.
I'm going to factor the
u out on the left side
instead of where it originally
came on the right side of this.
You see the great news there?
This was actually well-organized
by your professor--
by accident.
So what do I do now?
This thing-- look.
I've got exactly here what
I've got inverted there.
So altogether, I have I minus
uv transpose plus this u,
this cancelled,
times v transpose.
So I get I. So it was just
this little sleight of hand,
where u came in on the right
and came out on the left side.
And there'd be a similar
formula with A in there.
So now, it's a
fair question, how
did anybody come up
with these formulas?
We're proving them correct
just by checking that they
give the identity matrix.
We should really
think how to find
the formula in the first place.
I could go back to this one.
How could you find that
formula in the first place?
Well, here is one way to do it.
This is then about "to
discover the formula."
And then, over here, let me put
over here "to use the formula,"
while I think of it.
And actually, I have
two uses in mind.
Use one would be to solve--
I'm just doing I.
Suppose I want to--
so this is my new
matrix uv transpose x
equals some right-hand side b.
Solve a linear system that
has that coefficient matrix.
The use two would be, in least
squares, a new measurement
or observation or data
point in these squares.
So what do I mean by this?
The old problem was Ax equal b.
And I'm thinking, when I'm
talking about least squares
here, I'm imagining
that A is rectangular.
Too many equations--
A is a tall, thin
matrix, just the kind
we've been talking about.
So that equation becomes--
of course, we know we go
to the normal equations--
A transpose Ax, the good
x, is A transpose b.
Now we get a new measurement.
So a new measurement, how
does a new measurement
change the problem?
So this is the old problem
before the measurement
comes in.
Now a new measurement arrives.
So that's another
b, a b M plus 1.
And we get another equation.
We get another equation.
That's the new
measurement, new point
to get this straight line
it's trying to stay close to.
So we'll call this equation--
I don't know what
we should call it.
Maybe it'll be one more row.
So now, old now is becoming new.
I'm sort of more excited about
this than proving the formula.
So I'll just keep going.
So there is our M
measurements, M being large,
A being a tall, thin matrix.
And now we're going to
give it one more row.
We're going to make
it even taller,
say maybe, v transpose
times this same x is some b
new, or something like that.
So there's one more row,
one more measurement.
So what happens to
the normal equation?
This makes it even more likely.
There's another point, hoping
that a straight line will
go through.
But if we give it
one more point,
there is even less chance of
a straight line going exactly
through.
But still, so what do I--
this is my new matrix.
So what's my new
normal equation?
The new normal equation,
the A, or transpose--
the A has got a new row.
A has got a new row.
So a transpose will
have a new column.
I'm just copying
the normal equation,
but I'm giving it its new thing.
It's got a new column.
That is my A with a new row.
This is my x hat, my
least squares answer, new.
And A transpose is this.
A transpose with a new, now,
column times b, so b and b new.
Pretty OK with this.
Do you see that this is
the new normal equation?
I'm using the new matrix
and the new right-hand side.
And just one more
data point has come
into the system from the sensor.
And what's the key point here?
The key point is I
don't want to recompute.
I don't want to multiply
that matrix again.
I don't want to start over.
I don't want to compute this A
transpose times that A. I want
to use what I've already done.
If I multiply
those two together,
what do I actually get?
So this is, I'm adding a new
column here and a new row here.
Tell me what you think
the answer is, and then
let's just see why.
I'm asking you what
that matrix is.
What do you think?
Start me out, anyway.
I'm just asking for ordinary
matrix multiplication.
Well, I guess I'm
asking you to do it
columns times rows since that's
what 18 and 6.5 specializes in.
So I think I have that
times that, A transpose A,
plus one new column
times one new row.
vv transpose is
multiplying this x hat new.
And over on the right
side, I get whatever I had,
the A transpose b
old and the v b new.
But let me come back to that,
because that really shows you
why you must understand
matrix multiplication,
both the usual
row times column--
but that would not be
so attractive here--
and also the new way
as columns times rows.
Because when I see it
as columns times rows,
I see that I have the same
columns and same rows there.
So that's just what
I already knew.
And then I have one new
column times one new row.
Of course, that's column n plus
1, and that's a row n plus 1.
And they give that rank 1.
It's a rank 1 change in A
transpose A. It's a rank 1
change in A transpose A.
So this is like part
of least squares.
I mean, you can see the
relevance in a real problem.
You maybe have a
missile flying along.
You've sent up a
satellite, GPS satellite.
You're tracking it.
More data comes in.
The data is just
one more position.
The tracker isn't perfect.
So we're going to fit--
well, here I'm fitting
a straight line, maybe.
But we're fitting to the data.
And the only change in the
left-hand, the big problem,
the big part of the computation
is the A transpose A part.
And it's just changed
by rank 1, or by rank k,
if we had k new data points.
If we had k new data
points, then this
would be a rank k matrix.
So you see, then
I go back here--
well, OK.
Now I'm perturbing
A transpose A.
And I haven't given a
formula for that one yet.
I've only perturbed up
to, now, the identity.
But you can believe, since all
these formulas are working,
that Sherman or
Morrison or Woodbury
came up with the correct
perturbation for A transpose A.
So I'm sort of happy that,
that application, so natural,
came out so simply.
While I'm on that
sort of subject,
have you ever heard
of the Kalman filter?
So that Kalman filter,
what's that about?
It's about exactly this.
It's about dynamic
least squares.
It's about least
squares problems
in which new data is coming in.
That's what the Kalman
filter-- or in other words,
let me just write a
couple of words up here.
This is really
recursive least squares.
Recursive least squares--
what I mean by recursive
is new data comes in.
It changes the answer, but
it doesn't change our method.
And then the Kalman filter
is a very, very big deal
in guidance.
If you're sending up a missile,
a satellite, you track it.
You do just what I've
been discussing here.
But the Kalman filter is--
it's got more possibilities
built in than this one.
This is the simplest
update possible.
And it would go
in this category.
Kalman went beyond
a standard update.
How did he go beyond?
Let's see.
If I've used the
words Kalman filter,
I should tell you what
it is that Kalman does
and what is that
least squares problem.
It's just part of general
knowledge, it seems to me.
So what is it, more gen--
what are the additional pieces?
You've seen the main idea here
of getting a simple recursive
step that doesn't
require recomputing all
that you did before.
And of course, to
this inverse, I'm
going to apply the
Sherman-Morrison-Woodbury
formula.
So I'll use the inverse
that I had before.
And this will be a rank 1--
this is a rank 1
perturbation of that.
I'm looking here at A
transpose A. Over there,
I was looking at,
I just called it A.
Or I even called it
the identity matrix.
But it's whatever
matrix you have here
with a rank 1 perturbation.
And the whole thing
has to be inverted.
And so I was going to
say what is additional,
just so you know
about Kalman filters.
So two things are additional.
The point is Kalman filters
are for dynamic least squares.
I would say dynamic squares.
And so there are two ingredients
that you haven't seen here.
One ingredient is
the idea of using
the covariance matrix,
which tells you
how errors are correlated.
So that would be
weighted least squares,
or correlated least squares.
So these squares-- let
me just remind you,
if I can write it here.
So least squares-- standard.
Standard meaning that
data is not correlated.
It all has the same variance.
These are the statistics
words that I'm
using last time and this, but
that I'll talk about properly.
So the standard
one is the covari--
the standard means covariance
equal the identity matrix.
You're doing Gaussian
normal probability
but with just standard
Gaussians, standard Gaussians.
So that's one aspect, which
in the work of the Draper lab,
let's say, they
have to think, OK,
they're getting sensors,
different kinds of sensors,
with different accuracies,
different reliability.
So they have to take account
of the covariance matrix.
Then the other point is--
and also-- so that
was point one.
Point two is the dynamic part.
There is a state equation.
So I'm really into the
edge of control theory.
So let me just use some
words here that you've seen,
if you've--
so control theory
has state equation.
What's a state equation?
What is the state?
This is the position,
in my example,
is the position
of the satellite.
So are we looking for
a fixed satellite?
Certainly not.
The satellite is moving.
So this state equation tells
me how much the satellite--
it's Newton's law-- tells me
where the satellite should be.
Where am I looking?
And then the least
squares tells me, it says,
look around that sort
of median position
for the actual position
that the data is giving.
So just to say--
let me-- let me summarize this.
The Kalman filter is a
significantly improved version
of recursive least squares.
That's recursive least squares.
New measurement comes
in, changes things
but leaves a big part unchanged.
And you find that new x hat.
With a Kalman filter, there's an
covariance matrix in the middle
here.
That's where
covariance matrices go.
That's matrix covariance, or
inverse covariance, times that.
And oh, why don't we see the
covariances at the right time?
So maybe those minutes
that I've occupied
were just really to get you to
hear that name for the simplest
update.
And Kalman's name for
a more general update.
Done.
Oh, this is also to be done.
Where is-- yeah.
No-- up at the top.
I seem to be into the
applications here.
I promised how to
discover the formula.
Maybe I'll never know.
Because I'm really
more interested in,
what's it good for?
Use number one, now, I'm backing
up to the easy, easy question.
Suppose I had-- and let me even
change the matrix to A here.
It makes it more realistic.
I'm going to copy
that here, fully
on discovering the formula.
For the moment,
let's just use it.
So I suppose that Au
is b is solved for u.
Now, now solve A plus--
or minus a rank-- let me do the
rank 1, A minus uv transpose b.
What's-- x.
This is the problem that I
really would like to solve.
Let me just be sure
I'm doing this right.
It's similar to what we had
in the Kalman situation.
Suppose I've solved one problem.
But now I perturb
the matrix by rank 1.
So I have a new problem
with a new answer.
And I want to get
that answer quickly.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Are the u's
related in those two lines?
GILBERT STRANG: Oh, no.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
Let's call this guy
z, or w, maybe w.
So thank you.
That's great.
So that's what
I've solved for w.
In other words, I have
found A inverse b.
And I want to find the
answer to that new question.
So I've perturbed the matrix.
It's the coefficient
matrix in a linear system.
And I just want to solve
that linear system.
Now, so if I didn't know
anything about the formulas,
I would have a new matrix here.
It would take n cube steps
to do elimination and get
the new answer.
But the point is to
use the old answer.
The point is to
And now let me just
say what this is.
And it's problem
three in this section.
So in other words, we know
about A. We've solved that one.
So what I'm going to do, instead
of solving a whole new problem,
I'm going to--
so quickly is the idea.
And here's the idea.
I've solved that one.
And I'm going to solve
a second problem,
also solve, A with
the same matrix A--
oops-- A times what
shall I call the unknown?
There's z equal u.
So this is my problem.
I know the u and v transpose.
But I don't really want to
find the inverse of this matrix
from scratch.
So the idea is
that if I suitably
combine the solutions
to the original problem,
the original solution
w, and the solution
to this problem with the new
guy u there, that somehow,
by combining the w and the z,
I'm going to get this answer x.
That's where I'm headed.
That's where I'm headed, that
by figuring out w and z-- so
do you see what I've done?
With the matrix A, I've
solved two problems.
Does that take twice as long?
If I have the same matrix A but
different right-hand sides, b
and u, if I factor A into
Lu, all the hard work
is done there on the left side.
All the work is
done in finding Lu.
And then I just back substitute
to find the second solution.
This is so fundamental
that I'm emphasizing it,
that if you have multiple
right-hand sides,
you don't every time go back
and work on the left side.
The left side with
the same matrix A,
just would do the same stuff.
The same rows and pivots
and all that stuff
will happen because it's the
same A. You just attach--
you really just stick
a second column--
really, the fast way
to do it is A wz.
The two solutions come
from the b and the u.
I've just put the
two problems together
to emphasize that the
matrix A is the same.
This is where most
of the work goes.
But it only goes there once.
That's the point.
Then finally, I'm supposed to--
the notes are
supposed to tell me
how to combine the two answers
w and z to get the answer x.
So let me write that down.
And that will be
use number one of
the Sherman-Morrison-Woodbury
formula.
So I'm planning to
just write it down.
According to this, step
two is the answer we want,
here written x--
so I haven't used the same
letters as in the notes--
is the original w--
good-- and then a change.
Because I've
changed the problem.
So I'm going to
change the answer.
But the thing is,
to get this answer,
I have to divide by that
determinant wherever it was,
the--
oh, yeah, the--
I'm sorry.
I'm using an A here, and I
haven't given you the formula
for A. So that'll have to wait.
So I'll put determinant here.
And Sherman, Morrison,
Woodbury figured that out.
And then-- oh, I'm sorry.
We know what that is.
We want 1 minus v transpose z.
So it's the v from here,
1 minus v transpose.
And it's the z there.
Oh, yeah.
This is good.
So I'm going to get a formula
that changes the solution
w by a term that we recognize is
coming from Sherman, Morrison,
Woodbury.
And that term in the
numerator is a multiple of zx.
So I'm using w--
yes-- w times--
sorry-- times x, which was--
I'm sorry.
w is xv.
So the v here, I'm just using--
the v is the same
v. So v transpose z,
I think that's got it.
So again, the point was to--
x doesn't appear here, because
that's what I'm after--
is to use the w and
the z, the w and the z.
And I have to use, of course,
the v. And I have to use the u.
And that got used here.
So everything that had
to be used got used.
And that was the answer.
So that's the basic
use, is, if I perturb
the problem, the
left-hand side, what's
the change in the solution?
Over here with least
squares, it was the same.
I perturbed the left-hand side.
But because it
was least squares,
there was an A transpose
A to deal with.
So this was one
level more difficult,
because it involved
A transpose A's.
And here, it was just
straightforward A. So, yes?
Thanks.
AUDIENCE: Would it
be also a good idea--
so you have A minus uv transpose
x plus b-- to write A minus Az
b transpose x equals b?
I'm backtracking on the left.
GILBERT STRANG: I could
probably do this other ways.
Yeah.
I hope you follow up on
that and write it down.
So maybe what I've done is what
my goal was for today, first,
to show you the formula
for the inverse; second,
to recognize that it has
interesting importance
that a rank k
change in the matrix
brings a rank k change in the
inverse, and that we can--
the formula says to
invert an n by n matrix,
you can switch an
inverted k by k matrix.
And then I spoke about a
couple of the applications.
So the only thing
I have not done
is to give you the full
Sherman-Morrison-Woodbury
formula, the one with an A,
the one that's up on the right.
Can I do that finally?
You can probably guess
what it's going to be.
Where is-- there's got to
be one more blackboard.
So here
Sherman-Morrison-Woodbury.
And what's the complete thing?
It's A minus uv
transpose inverse.
So this is n by n.
And it's an A now instead
of an identity matrix.
That's the difference.
And this is n by k, k by n.
So it's rank k perturbation.
And start me out on the formula.
What's the first
thing I have to write?
AUDIENCE: A inverse.
GILBERT STRANG: A inverse.
So I start with A inverse.
And then I subtract something.
And it's going to be a
copy of this, except--
well, maybe it's
just a perfect copy.
Maybe I just need the u.
I'm going from that left board.
Now, Ik, what do
I put it in there?
I am going to have to look.
So we're writing down now
the formula, the full scale--
OK.
Oh, all right.
Here it is.
There is an A inverse u.
Now comes that
whole thing inverted
that you'll expect, I minus
v transpose A inverse u,
all inverse.
And then there's another two
pieces, v transpose A inverse.
So I didn't look ahead to
get it at all on one line.
But do you see what--
this is the-- oh, that's
probably-- is that--
yeah.
That's the identity.
Because we've got
enough A inverses.
I believe that's the final,
ultimate formula of life
here, that we've
changed it by rank k.
Here's the original inverse.
And presumably, this
is a rank k change.
That will be a rank k change.
And it only requires us to
compute that inverse, where
that's a k by k matrix.
Thank you for allowing this,
our 50 minutes of formulas.
So that's really
what that comes to.
So that's section 4.1 of the
notes with some applications.
And we will move on to other
circumstances of low rank.
Good.
Thank you.